hello John DeBakey hello Jacob
pleasure to be here good to have you on
a man possessed by the search for wisdom
it seems at times yeah that's very much
insofar as we are possessed by love yeah
I think so yes that would be a fair way
of putting it
I was watching I've been you know
following your awakening from the
meaning crisis series which is a just
amazing in terms of breath just the
amount of books that are channeling
through your brain and body obviously
been a sort of student of the day logos
conversations that you've been having
this year with people like Jordan and
guy and just Chris of course and Andrew
Tiger and Johannes and quite a network
of people which by the way just sort of
appreciate the way that you're always
kind of giving recognition to all of the
people's work that's going into to what
you're doing I think that's important do
I think it's very important to do yeah
it's really there's a sense of like when
John is articulating John's point you're
actually getting like a map of the whole
sort of terrain of things which has come
into it yeah and thank you for saying
that
and also to give to give recognition to
you know the distributed cognition
that's actually at work and to really
I'm really trying to exemplify even when
I'm speaking mana logically I want to
try to emphasize that deep reasoned deep
reflection the insight deep questioning
are ultimately all biological in nature
I'm trying to break I'm trying to on in
many ways a mini manner right trying to
break out of this you know this
monolithic
monistic mind like there we have this
picture of the mind is this completely
self enclosed self discourse saying
subterra like all of that that that
completely self-imposed understanding of
who and what are our meaning making is
and what the mind is and this is also
like I mentioned in many places you've
probably seen this is not much in
consonance with a movement within
cognitive science called for econo
science which is to try not see the mind
as something I possess in my head but
something that I participate in between
my brain and my body and my embodied
brain and the world right and so there's
a deep connection between that model of
the mind that is emerging in carbon
science which i think is fundamentally
on the right track and the the ancient
ideas of that reason and reflection
insight aspiration all these things are
inherently biological in nature so not
only do I feel there's a moral point
which is significant and important to
share in credit I want to point to
distributed cognition and I want to
point to dialogical rationality and try
to exemplify them as much as possible so
that people can see not just not just
you know here what I'm referring to but
they can see it exemplify and how I'm
trying to practice it before them so
it's actually very important to me it's
it's it's like practice for me in a deep
sense mmm part of much is part of like
my spiritual practice to try and do that
more and more and more it's it seems
like it's a kind of it's like a method
relationship there's being represented
that kind of goes up and down all of the
levels of the stack of being you know
it's kind of yeah the relationship would
world is dialogic and then within that
you know there's the intertext reality
sorry I'm getting stupid email
notification
figure out and send this off it's it's
in relationship with world and then
within self a dialogue between all of
the things that are coming from well you
know mother father and philosophers and
everything I think that's I think that's
really important so that affords me an
opportunity to balance things out a
little bit because for obvious reasons
I've been emphasizing the what Chris and
I mr. McMaster Pietro and I call the
horizontal aspects of dialectic
dialectic is the sacred technology that
scaffolds you into the process of the
logos it's like it's like they say a set
of directions to direct your attention
and the way you're coupling to the world
so that Villalobos can be imported but
one of the directions of dialectic is
the horizontal it's the interpersonal
one and that's the one that I get to
practice with guy and Jordan and Chris
and Andrew Sweeney etc Jack Stein but
what you just mentioned is also right
and this was integral to Plato the
Platonic model right there's also what
you might call the vertical that intra
ontological that you use you have to
sort of practice individually it's seen
in bachelor says we're always alone with
others which i think is total of one of
those books which is a great way of
putting it but this this this as you
said this this how you meant what Plato
does and there were in the Republic
where the model of the justice in the
city is reflected in the model of the
justice between the elements of the
psyche and vice-versa and they merge
mutually afford and conform to each
other so you you it's exactly that that
inner via logos and that outer D logos
are actually just like like the left and
right fields of vision that you see
through into depth perception you're
always you're always looking through
them to what what is what grounds the
two of them together and that's when
when that starts to happen that's when
you really get a sense feeler
it's a part of what I'm going to deal in
the in the next series after Socrates is
I'm going to I mean I'm going to talk a
lot about the horizontal because you've
seen a lot of the work I've been doing
with a lot of people that are I owe a
lot to but I'll also be bringing out
that vertical and then ensuring how
they're integrated together so that I
mean that that's very exciting for me
because when those two resonate with
each other you get you get you get to a
place that is a field of grounding and
affording of profound transformation a
lot of pathways opening up this is
you're saying all of that things that
I've been kind of thinking about
recently I mean first and foremost
there's something about the way in which
the the mystic or the or the or the
wisdom teacher or the religious prophet
very often is speaking in in
relationship to the environment very
often kind of using Matt's boards
derived from nature or speaking in
Powerball and I think there's some
relationship between this and the the
way in which our cognition takes place
outside of our bodies in relationship to
the aesthetic of the environment yeah I
think that's a very astute observation
there is I think a deep continuity and
that's a phrase that my my friend and
colleague
Evan Thompson has introduced into for
e-card saw but I think there's a deep
continuity between the ineffable and and
enacted mystery of everyday cognition
and the ineffable and enacted mystery of
some of our most ultimate experiences
and I'm working on a book with anybody
on that's called the cognitive
continuum from insight to enlightenment
that the machinery that you are using I
was I had mentioned that I was reading
I'm reading this book right now by
Esther like not me longing to know was
recommended to me and she is actually
making a very convergent argument it's
convergent because both she and I are
deeply influenced by the work of Michael
Polanyi
but there's a deep continuity I want to
use her example because it's a let me
just use an analogy
she's not - because I if there's similar
to some other ones I use but it's a new
one so I don't haven't you seen that
there's these called magic five pictures
and there's a bunch of colored dots and
you sort of move the picture you do the
zoom in/out optimal gripping and then
what will happen is it will suddenly
snap you'll get this aha you'll get an
insight experience and something you'll
see a three-dimensional dolphin leaping
out of the water and it just sort of
catches right and she talks about how
like you go from looking at you you'll
recognize some of this language so
looking through here you go from sort of
seeing all the dots to seeing the
dolphins seeing a deeper dimension and
the point is on that's just an
extraordinary example of something we're
doing moment to moment you're doing it
right now you're taking all the pixels
on your screen right and the complicated
and subtle motions of changes and
variants and color and hue of my face
and you're making a face and and then
you're looking through that face into my
mind and into my thoughts and you're
doing it like that and if I asked you
how do you view it how do you get that
depth that ontological depth perception
you very well I don't know it's and it
has an aspect of insight and revelation
and you have to sort of you know entrust
yourself to an embodied process and a
skillful way of coupling to the world
and then she's making the argument and
she's at the s2 that's where I differ
from her but she says that's similar to
how we how we see God right and and and
what I think she meaning is that there's
a continuity between our most mystical
experiences and our most everyday
experience because our everyday
experience contained
some of that mystery that become more
aware of when when it is mystery that's
embedded within an AW experience so I
think there is in fact I think what
you're saying there is exactly right I
think there it's not just that the
wisdom teachers are mystics are you know
using metaphor I think they're actually
affording a realization of the
continuity between your everyday
experience and your ultimate experiences
I mean this is captured in Zen right
that very the famous is in parable you
know before I did before I did Zen
mountains were mountains and rivers were
rivers while I was doing Zen mountains
are work mountains and rivers or rivers
and then I was when I was done doing Zen
mountains were mountains and rivers or
rivers notice how I have to use my
intonation you can make the difference
right and and so it's very important and
that's what I'm talking or a while but
this is an accrual point this there's
the sense of deep continuity is an
alternative way of relating the
transcendent to the imminent that breaks
away from sort of the two worlds
mythology that has tended to build an
inaccessible Fortress of mystique around
the transcendent and and and and and
then make it very easily translatable
into the absurd impossible that can just
be ignored
right but if I make you realize that
that Ultimo and it is that ultimate is
awe-inspiring and it is do of reverence
I'm not denying that but if I make you
realize that that is has a deep
continuity with how you're seeing my
face then you can't dismiss it or ignore
it as an input as an absurdity
possibility and so I want to try and
break out of the two worlds mythology
and the one that builds the spiritual as
this
you know it's this thing that is
fortified by supernatural istic mystique
and so that's why I got very excited by
what you said because it's an insight
right that points to an alternative way
an alternative grammar of thinking about
what these teachers have said to us that
can perhaps we'll move it from a two
worlds mythology in which it has been
entrusted what were you saying John
thank you
thank you that's really nice I love just
like throwing the piece out and then
watching you do a little transformation
on it and then it's kind of more exalted
it's so I've been I'm in Athens right
now and I have been for the last three
months so staying with my parents Oh
Warren teen you're in Athens Greece yes
Wow that's a nice place yeah it's been
probably more positive than a few
people's quarantine difficult at times
of course but one of the things I've
been doing is spending a lot of time in
Greek Orthodox churches just so the
church from a different you know yep my
I grew up with the Anglican Church but
one of the things you know and Anna is
you know I'm kind of sitting in presence
and observing observing the space and
observing the icons and so forth the
first thing is you see the difference
with the way that the people the Greek
cultural relationship with it they don't
really look around and look up in the
way that I'm doing they kind of just
shuffle in go straight to the icon at
the front and kiss the icon and there's
kind of a very private slightly viewed
with shamed kind of a feeling thing
going on and the the aesthetic of the
churches and I'm definitely a sort of
believer in the need to build
transcendence environment but it always
has this feeling of like just being
on the cusp of something but you can't
get quite get it yeah you know it's like
beautiful and golden and the eye of
horus is up there somewhere looking out
at you but it's a doorway and a little
railing and then behind that maybe a cat
and then behind that something else and
then you got in the street and then you
can actually find the real deal
hopefully and I think when you get
closer to the real deal you almost have
to afford space for the real deal to
reveal itself I've been having you know
a lot of my inquiry has really just been
paying very close attention to phenomena
as arising and so I'll kind of see like
I've started noticing very briefly those
moments in which something appears in my
field which I later realized as a
cyclist but for a moment my brain hasn't
quite figured out yeah yeah
first liminal yeah thing and the curious
part about that is the quality of what
you experience when it's in the liminal
not form space is very Saturn setting
really it's kind of what you are
bringing to it as much as anything I
want to build out one more sort of piece
for you I was watching your dialogue
with Jordan Peterson from years ago yeah
five years but by the way have another I
wish we could have another well I think
what was really shining out for me was
the partly this kind of journey from
like the IDW to what you're doing and
how what you're doing is so much more
bringing out that like collaborative
dialogic and you know like figuring out
how to really like achieve intimacy and
you know the basic interpersonal stuff
is actually happening but with Jordan
one of the things that you agreed on was
that the meaning cry
which can be above you know the
perennial continual crisis of being that
the very specific historical trajectory
of meaning crisis has different
inflection points and you can go back to
World War two you can go back to the
time of of Nietzsche you can go back to
Descartes you can go back to man's
breakage with the natural world
yeah and so what I'd like to do now is
present a piece which is kind of just
been in my head and esoteric and see if
we can bring it in and it's notion of
I've called it like the landscape of
trauma and what it is is an inquiry into
the nature of trauma which is revealing
of a lot of these kind of elements of
reality that you speak to the sort of
inexplicable 'ti of people with past
traumas finding themselves finding other
people in the world and coming into
relationship with them neither of em
being conscious of it and this kind of
being invisible but meaningful like
attractor and force and the way in which
trauma is stored in the body as a as a
really embodied property of being as a
kind of disconnection from aspects of
self it seems to me super tied up with
embodied cognition and meters Jordan
kept on talking about like you know
bringing order as like a way of kind of
narrowing in the balance of chaos and
for me like it's I can see a way in
which the there's a landscape of trauma
which we are the embodied inheritors of
and are coming back into relationship
with spirituality in nature is really
like a going down and into and releasing
all of those like you know traumas
traumas of the 20th century alone
anomalous you know I was my grandfather
was in the Second World War
his father was in the First World War
before that they lived in under awful
Victorian English culture and you know
and then we can go all the way back to
how is it that they became so alienated
from nature in the first place so yeah I
wanted to kind of to hear how you might
play with play with that notion well you
throw three things that and I don't
think they're happenstance and it's
interesting how there's often a
gathering of things together beyond sort
of our egocentric awareness or father
gathered together so you you well you
you you've brought up Eastern Orthodox
Christianity and then you talked about
sort of the the liminal place where you
can wear since making is you can get a
more direct phenomenological awareness
of it and how set and setting mattered
and then and then you moved into the
fact that responding to the meaning
crisis and this is something I need to
talk more about I'm going to talk about
though and this is you know the work of
Levine and others about dealing with
trauma and both collective and
individual trauma and the way in which
trauma gets embodied in individuals and
the way it gets embedded into social
systems and so why do I think all of
those relate to each other well first of
all it's interesting that neoplatonism
actually well sorry Eastern Orthodox
Christianity I should put it and the
person to talk to you about this before
Jonathan cause Oh Jonathan's a colleague
of mine and we have a very good
relationship I've got to meet him once
in person and I really really respect
what he has to but he has a saying he's
a he he's very much a proponent of
Eastern
Orthodox Christianity but one of the
things that's clear in Eastern Orthodox
Christianity is the way it brings the
Neoplatonic project that we were talking
about earlier the vertical and the
horizontal of trying to refine and
clarify intelligibility so as to enhance
ontological depth perception and to know
do the an agog a do the ascent right but
that Neoplatonic element which is very
present
Eastern Orthodox Christianity has been
integrated with aspects of Christianity
that have to do with exactly what you're
talking about which have to do with
trauma salvation ultimately means
healing and the healing that's being
dealt with there is the sense that we
are in some sense a broken bent damaged
and that that is something that has to
be addressed in embodied fashion this is
part of the mythology of the Incarnation
the logos has to be embodied in order to
not only bring us the intelligibility of
the logos but to confront the trauma
that we embody as people and so that's
being brought together in the
Neoplatonic Christianity with the
healing the trauma but also the ascent
of intelligibility at the logos and the
healing the logos and the salvation come
together in the Incarnation which is an
ancient word for embodiment right and
then the point that that what you
liminal that puts you into the place
right
the place where the icon actually sits
the icon sits and you already referenced
it something that's you can see but it's
just beyond your grasp and that that's a
liminal like the liminality that you're
describing phenomenologically you can
see it but you can't quite see through
it you can see it but you can't quite
see what it means and you're on that
space of trying to actively make sense
and notice how all these are circling
around each other in a very sort of
pregnant chasuble they're sort of
bouncing off each other and connect the
and coupling attracting to each other
and affording each other
articulating each other and I don't
think that's coincidence I think that we
need to deal deeply with the integration
of those three which is the and think
about the virtues that are needed for
each perhaps as a way of thinking about
it
so intelligibility requires by the the
the practice of the dialectic and what
that would would demand from us but that
has at its heart a kind of receptivity
to the anomalous to the liminal to the
not yet so that I can move beyond where
I am and but that receptivity is a mesh
is bound up inseparably with dealing in
the ways in which I enclosed often
receptivity because of trauma and that
if I can't release if I can't open
myself up beyond that Michel Washington
calls it body armor which i think is a
wonderful way of putting it but I can't
I can't learn to become aware of it and
let it go which is not something you can
pretty much done something you can do on
your own and an autodidact the classroom
you need you need other people in a very
sort of profound way which is why of
course you're also find yourself going
into the ecclesia going into the church
right or going into the sangha so i
think that you're again it's interesting
how you can I can see a load Heraclitus
said don't listen to me but listen to
the logos in my speech so in through
your speech I can I can sense our logos
in the way in in how these things are
coming together and and what we're doing
hopefully together is realizing how they
belong together and what they're
pointing us towards they're pointing us
towards the deep integration between an
agog a yeah you know an enhancement of
ontological depth perception a courage
and a willingness to move into a limo
and the anomalous and relate to it as as
something of wonder but that that cannot
be undertaken without it is necessarily
bound up with the healing of the trauma
that blocks are appropriate receptivity
and that that is something that has to
happen biologically this is again where
I think we need something like a
religion that's not a religion and not
just an ideology and not just a personal
belief system eccentric central so yeah
that's why I was bored respond to what
he said it's incredibly the Stewart done
very you have seen through the ruse of
my language into what into what sort of
is holding me captive right now now
that's a way to put it but I was telling
you a little bit before that my you know
might big inquiry the piece that I'm
sort of most bringing to this discourse
is from an understanding of Islam and
Islam is relationship to the West but
now I find myself almost kind of
stepping back a little bit from that
inquiry and I'm trying to to figure out
the Jesus piece which is you know its
salient incredibly to to what you're
saying because I grew up in a Christian
context imbued with real real faith you
know the the use of the of the name of
Jesus was sort of just all over my early
childhood and was in a community
contacts until the age of 10 or 11 so
for me a big pot of passing it all out
has been sort of I think for most people
the worst thing about Christianity or
the Christ lineage is Christians and the
church my father was a
and a religious man has been a long time
banging his head against the walls of
the the culture and institutions of the
church so I guess what I'm what what it
feels to me is that so much of the
Christianity that I came from was there
was a celebration of arrival it's like
we we are broken and we have arrived but
have we yet done the requisite work and
drawn upon the vast array of resources
available to us in order to enable that
know what would actually what we're
doing is is really constraining
ourselves in very limited bands of
thinking and I've been sort of
dialoguing a little bit with some people
on various journeys like some are still
Christians and we're kind of moving out
of it into something else and this
feeling of like the way that that like
cognitive grammar is constrained by
reference to things that they already
know in the presupposition that that the
answers are already there and for me so
much of this has been like I took the I
mean it's super resonant with with your
path from what I know in the sense that
I kind of went atheist went agnostic and
then went by a completely different
route to arrive at some sense of
spirituality and relationship to mystery
and contemplative practices and all of
this stuff like all of that has occurred
for me up until this point without any
reference to to Christianity really or
even the Bible or the figure of Christ
so now with all of that I can go out and
go back and I'm reading temptation and
you know I've always had a weird
fascination with the experience of
churches and so that's kind of where I'm
at and I think you're kind of there as
well a little bit I think very much I
mean we have very similar backgrounds I
was brought up a Christian also
their self deeply committed in that but
also and I think it's fair to use this
word and it's relevant to what we were
just talking about up that also deeply
traumatized by it and then trying to
work out right relationship to
Christianity is something that I've
needed to do obviously individually but
it's also resonant with you know I don't
know if I would this refers to but the
West's relationship the Commonwealth
that came out of Christendom like it
still has some relationship deep
relationship to the cultural cognitive
grammar of Christianity and trying to
work out inside women very quickly you
know even if it's not traumatizing you
know even if the transmission and the
discipline is not traumatizing the
absence of the working through trauma in
relationship some sort of spiritual
framework is in itself the guarantor of
the transmission of the trauma of the
past because we almost all of us the
descendents of countless Wars and you
know awful things that happened in
social context where there was no
possibility of releasing that trapped
energy I think that's one said that the
idea that we have built many patterns
complex patterns of interaction of
interest psychically and interpersonally
and this is sort of a naturalistic
version of karma if you want that sort
of permeate and sub perpetuate through
us
and through our culture in our
relationship to each other and a
relationship to the environment I mean
we are experiencing the trauma you know
that we've traumatized the environment
and it's now that's now coming back to
us in deeply powerfully so I think
everything I mean deep in agreement with
with your interjection I think it's very
very important I think what's
interesting is if we could put the two
of these together oh sorry I'm gonna
pour
this because what what was happening
between us a few minutes ago was I see
that is very much the heritage from
Socrates that idea of discourse as a way
of reducing drawing out of trying to
like like the magic I see through and
try to realize the logos that's
occurring between us and what you're
saying and possibly in what I'm saying
but I direct more attention to what
you're saying and how that could perhaps
be reintegrated with the attempt to come
into right relationship with Jesus as a
sage and Christianity as a cultural
historical phenomena because I think
we're facing the same thing we have to
try and draw out as much that's how I
used to use the word Salvage but I'm now
moving more towards this idea of
adducing trying to draw out from
Christianity in a Socratic fashion what
can be drawn out in a way that is
integrated with trying to deal with both
the personal and the collective trauma
and the legacies of trauma and that's a
very very tricky thing to do because and
we can see secular versions of this
throughout the culture Christianity
valorizes the traumatized individual at
the center of Christianity is the cross
which is deep it which is a deep trauma
induction device
I mean it's designed to terror and they
humiliate a person is it's designed you
don't just kill the person on the cross
you traumatize them to death
and so Christianity can too can too
readily valorize the trauma as opposed
to responding to the trauma and we
we can we can get into worshipping the
victim rather than dealing with trauma
and those are not the same thing those
are not the same thing and so trying to
do this Socratic deduction of
Christianity and break free from the two
worlds mythology is also bound up with
but really wrestling with the the
difficult relationship that Christianity
has to follow precisely because it it
valorizes and worships the traumatized
individual of the victim it can most
effectively mask and blind us to
actually dealing with trauma because it
has a look so deeply added it's like
it's like the magic eye picture all we
can see is the little picture
we're fascinating and we don't actually
get how we're supposed to see through it
and deal with it and so the thing that's
so close to you that you can't see it
yes yes it's like me cheese idea of the
shadow that you can't jump over or or
what Nietzsche in fact said of Socrates
he said I hate Socrates he's so close to
me I'm always fighting him and so that's
that's a sort of thing
I don't hate Christianity but
Christianity is so close to me I'm
always fighting it in that in that
hopefully respectful and joyful way
precisely because and this is something
that's I mean Thank You Jacob you really
taking me to the sort of the cutting
edge of my own reflection right now so I
appreciate that I want to I want to
genuinely thank you for that but this is
where I'm at right now but really trying
to understand right exactly what you're
saying that you know the the the
affordance of an agog a represent these
like that what you did the up and down
and then to dealing with trauma they're
inseparable abound together and there
and we have a traumatized relationship
with Christianity but it's made
especially problematic because of the
the way
trauma is actually valorized in
Christianity in a symbolic way I'm not
saying that's Christianity is
masochistic or sadistic I'm not saying
that I'm saying there was I think Gerard
is right there's a profound
understanding there of a tendencies to
scapegoat and project our trauma and all
that but it can be so lost because
Christianity has made this though
familiar and I think it's an odd thing
that people wear crosses around their
necks and they've lost how odd this is
imagine if someone carried around a
chain and had a guillotine on it we'd go
whoa what's wrong with you that's weird
and then then say well that's the
relationship of what I hold mode that's
a symbol of what I hold most sacred we
go
oh no but we've lost all of that in the
cross there's so many more pieces are
gonna have to talk about it again at
some point just to bring a couple of
them to bear I think was becoming
salient to me is like the way of
approaching the character of Christ or
the scripture for me has to be done in
the same way as one would approach a
work of literature like I don't think
it's a coincidence we have this great
lineage of like literary excitation of
the underlying meaning structures in the
story of the Rings so forth and this
this introduces a more interpretive mode
of understanding which is
and I think the other key component
which kind of Zack is talking a little
bit about and has you know kind of comes
a lot out of the kind of psychedelic
Terence Mckenna lineage for me as well
is about the primacy of experience and
and that the key one of the key sort of
axioms of making community work
meaningfully is going to be that the
individuals who constitute the community
and themselves capable of leaving it
going out and being on their own
yes are to getting direct relationship
to world and then you know coming back
in but there has to be that sort of yeah
and that's that's really speaks to that
experience that I was having in Orthodox
churches it's like you know because of
how much I've kind of opened myself up
I'm getting a lot more walking down the
street and observing day-to-day life
than I am
inside of the temple the temple is kind
of like a big you know some days I I
quite enjoy it and I find it
contemplative but very often it feels
like a bit of a trick almost like it's
it's like no let's try those two things
together so Tolkien and the recovery
theory right and so I think this is very
much the token had an idea that rent
there's two types of fantasy there's
escapism which you know in entertainment
and whatever right and then he had what
he liked father's recovery theory and
the idea is very much like what happens
with when an anthropologist goes to
another culture and has to go through
the different process of enculturation
and then the point is not just to see
that other culture that point is very
important it's a biological point it's
not to create a treatise or a monograph
the point is you and then when you
return to this culture you see your
culture of birth from the eyes of the
other culture and you see it and you
recover it you have an insight into it
in a way you didn't and going into a
church should be like that it should be
like
and I mean this respectfully it should
be a an enacted fantasy that right makes
it possible for you to go out into the
restraint and recover that world more
powerfully I think in that sense
religious practice is very much like
augmented reality like you know the
heads-up display of the pilot or when
people are playing Pokemon on their
phones and it's getting like we create a
kind of imaginal pretense but not
because it's false or or entertaining
what it does is it actually takes us out
of the familiar so that we can recover
the familiar with unfamiliar eyes and we
can see it more deeply more profoundly I
think the point of going to church is
exactly what happens when you leave the
church not what's happening in the
church I teach my students the exact
same thing in meditation like the
medicine don't think of meditation as a
vacation think of an edge of it as an
education introducing right and it and
coming out of your your sitted practice
is an integral part of your practice
you're trying to carry over that affair
I'm metaphor transfer over what you've
cultivated in your your sitting to your
everyday consciousness cognition
character and community on its that
recovery that's the point of it I call
this the sometimes call this the
transworld
your your your you're not going you're
not moving between worlds you're going
into like a fantasy so in order to more
deep and I mean this again powerfully in
korban sense an imaginal thing so that
you can more deeply return to this world
in its depth and this is the correct
understanding of how to relate to the
mystical experience I think also you
know bringing in the literary component
its Frodo leaves the Shia goes on a big
journey but at some point there's like
the return to the Shire but the Shire is
not the same as before he went on the
journey that's right that's right
that's right it's and he's not the same
either
right now we've left the Shire and now
we're just saying like oh none of that
you know the last two thousand years
don't worry about any of
wherever well we have left the Shire and
we haven't we're still a mess like we
were talking about earlier and a lot of
ways but yeah I think if we could I
really think I would really like to put
you into contact with Paul van der clay
and get you to go on his show and have a
discussion with him I think he'd be very
interested in having a discussion with
you I've been thinking about reaching
out to him so that's if you'd like to
you know once this video is available
and then I can use it as a link and
introduce you to him and I think he'd be
very interested in talking to you Jacob
I have to go soon but a couple things I
would like to since you've recorded this
as video I'd like to upload this to my
channel as well voices with her Bakey so
if you could send me the finals that
would be great and secondly I'd like to
request to have another discussion with
you because I found this one really
powerful and I swear you have a very
penetrating mind and I would like to and
I mean this again in a complimentary
fashion I'd like to play with you more
about it because I think it's it's
really well like I said it's really
reducing I feel very much there's a law
resonating between us I'd like to
explore it more it's a real honor to
those words from you John thank you the
honor is yours unfortunate like I said
you have to go and I want to thank you
but let's set up and let's talk again
soon like within two or three weeks
possible if you can give me these files
somehow because I really enjoyed what
happened here and I'd like I'd like it
to be more widely available to to my
listeners I guess that's where our
viewers and then also if I have that
link I want to connect you up with Paul
because I think I think it would be
lovely you had a conversation with them
all right yeah I'll get all that to you
and it's really good it feels like we're
just like arriving at something that
needs to be opened up yeah it's also
another reason why I'd like to get a
copy of this because I want to watch it
again and then you and I meet again and
try and get back into the
mentum of this and try and really
explore this because and I meant what I
said earlier I I always try to say what
I mean or mean what I mean what I say
but you really take me sort of to the
threshold but where I'm thinking right
now the threshold the liminal area right
and so I want to get back there again
and I foresee that I need your your help
in doing so so I would appreciate that
awesome John it's been great to have you
on and be good to have you on again or
I'll be on your channel or something but
I'll work it out and yeah
maybe you know let's get this one up on
the voices with Ravi key and maybe I'll
send you the link next time
and then I'll directly record it and we
can upload it there as well that's a
good idea
let's let's make that a point of action
going forward the more viewers the
merrier yeah you I really and you
understand of course and I don't think
this is well it's obviously biasing in
some way but I think right now it's also
heuristic that that's a helpful
heuristic there's a deep similarity
between our respective costs that's very
helpful very helpful for getting into to
the file eeeh you know that the the
appropriate kind of intimacy for for
dialectic so yeah I look forward to
talking to you again right next time
we'll talk about the horrors of
Christian rock music and a great
pleasure meeting you great pleasure
high fives John really